Rudolf Wunderlich Collection of James McNeill Whistler Exhibition Catalogs
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Rudolf Wunderlich collection of James McNeill Whistler exhibition catalogs
1903-1935
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Wunderlich, Rudolf
0.2 linear feet
The Rudolf Wunderlich collection of James McNeill Whistler exhibition catalogs date from 1903 through 1935. The collection consists of 0.2 linear feet of 19 exhibition catalogs listing artwork by James McNeill Whistler, and one periodical article analyzing Whistler's famous butterfly icon.
Biographical Note
Rudolf Wunderlich was the co-owner of Kennedy & Company, an art gallery in New York. His grandfather, Hermann Wunderlich, founded the gallery in 1874. (The name was changed from H. Wunderlich & Company to Kennedy & Company in 1912.) The gallery handled primarily fashionable prints, Old Master prints and a few of the contemporary artists, including James McNeill Whistler (1834-1903). Kennedy & Company was Whistler's first dealer in the United States, and the artist frequently spent time at the gallery. These Whistler exhibition catalogs apparently came from Rudolf Wunderlich's personal collection.
Scope and Content Note
The Rudolf Wunderlich collection of James McNeill Whistler exhibition catalogs spans the years 1903 to 1935, and measures 0.2 linear feet. The collection consists of 18 exhibition catalogs and 1 periodical article analyzing Whistler's trademark butterfly icon. In addition to the list of works on display, many catalogs include introductions that provide background on the artist and his work. Some also include notes on each individual piece of artwork. The catalogs represent exhibitions in London, New York, Paris, Boston, Buffalo, and Glasgow. One is in French. A few have notations and prices written in pencil, perhaps by Wunderlich. All but wwo of the catalogs appear in Research Libraries' Group's union database, RLIN; the two exceptions are marked [rare] in the container list.
Arrangement
Catalogs are arranged chronologically, then alphabetically by author. The article appears at the end of the collection. Bibliographic citations for the catalogs are based on entries in RLIN.
Index Terms
This collection is indexed in the online catalog of the Archives of American Art under the following terms:
Subjects:
Whistler, James McNeill, 1834-1903 -- Exhibitions
Provenance
The collection was donated by Rudolf Wunderlich in 1959.
Restrictions on Access
The collection is open for research. Use requires an appointment.
Series Descriptions/Container Listing
- Rudolf Wunderlich Collection of James McNeill Whistler Exhibition Catalogs, 1903-1935, undated, Series 1:; (Box 1; 0.2 linear feet)
  - Obach & Co. Exhibition of etchings by J. McNeil Whistler. London: The Company, 1903. (Box 1)
  - Copley Society. Loan collection: Oil paintings, water colors, pastels & drawings: Copley Hall, February 1904. Boston: Copley Society, 1904. (Box 1)
  - Grolier Club. Catalogue of etchings and dry-points by James McNeill Whistler exhibited by the Grolier Club ... from April 15th until May 7th, nineteen hundred and four. New York: De Vinne Press, 1904. (Box 1)
  - Rembrandt Gallery. Catalogue of an exhibition of lithographs by the late James McNeill Whistler exhibited at Robt. Dunthorne's The Rembrandt Gallery [rare]. London: Chiswick Press, 1904. (Box 1)
  - Palais de l'E´cole des beaux-arts. Exposition des oeuvres de James McNeill Whistler. Paris: Frazier-Soye, 1905. (Box 1)
  - Raleigh, Walter. In memoriam, James McNeill Whistler: A speech delivered by Prof. Walter Raleigh, at the Cafe´ Royal, London, at the banquet on the occasion of the opening of the Whistler memorial exhibition. London: [Heinemann], 1905. (Box 1)
  - Frederick Keppel & Co. Catalogue of an exhibition of etchings and drypoints by Whistler, with an introduction by Joseph Pennell. New York: De Vinne Press, 1907. (Box 1)
  - Grolier Club. Catalogue of lithographs by J. McN. Whistler exhibited at the Grolier Club April 4th to April 27th, 1907. [New York]: De Vinne Press, 1907. (Box 1)
  - Frederick Keppel & Co. Catalogue of an exhibition of etchings and dry-points by Whistler, with an introduction and notes especially compiled for this exhibition by Joseph Pennell. New York: De Vinne Press, 1909. (Box 1)
  - Albright Art Gallery. Oils, water colors, pastels & drawings by James McNeill Whistler, lent by Mr. Richard Canfield [rare]. 5p. Buffalo, N.Y.: Buffalo Fine Arts Academy, 1911. (Box 1)
  - Albright Art Gallery. Oils, water colors, pastels & drawings by James McNeill Whistler, lent by Richard Canfield. 49p. Buffalo, N.Y.: Buffalo Fine Arts Academy, 1911. (Box 1)
  - National Gallery of British Art. Catalogue of loan collection of works by James McNeill Whistler, (Room V.), July to October, 1912. London: Darling & Son, Ltd., 1912. (Box 1)
  - P. & D. Colnaghi & Obach. Loan exhibition of works by James McNeill Whistler to aid the Professional Classes War Relief Council. London: P. & D. Colnaghi & Obach, 1915. (Box 1)
  - Kennedy & Company. Catalogue of an exhibition of paintings, etchings, and lithographs by Whistler ... November-December, 1916. New York: Goerck Art Press, 1916. (Box 1)
  - Arden Gallery. P ortraits of Whistler and other Whistlerana: Loan collection, December 16th to January 6th. New York: Arden Gallery, [1918?]. (Box 1)
  - Anderson Galleries, Inc. The Walter H. Jessop collection of lithographs by Whistler: to be sold by auction, at eight-fifteen, Thursday evening, November twentieth, at the Anderson Galleries. New York: Douglas Taylor & Co, [1919]. (Box 1)
  - M. Knoedler & Co., Inc. A Whistler centenary, with an introduction by Howard Mansfield ... October 16th to November 17th, 1934. New York: M. Knoedler & Co., 1934. (Box 1)
  - University of Glasgow. Exhibition of works of art by James McNeill Whistler, together with personal memorials of the artist. Presented to the University by Miss R. Birnie Philip. Glasgow: University Press, 1935. (Box 1)
  - Pavière, Sydney H. "Whistler's Butterfly: A New Theory." The Bookman's Journal, p. 123-125[c.1919-1921]. (Box 1)